<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title></title>
    <link>https://michelesantacatterina.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content on </description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 15 Oct 2017 00:00:00 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Talks &amp; Posters</title>
      <link>https://michelesantacatterina.github.io/old-home/talks/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://michelesantacatterina.github.io/old-home/talks/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Clarifying identification and estimation of treatment effects in the Sequential Parallel Comparison Design</title>
      <link>https://michelesantacatterina.github.io/publication/spcd/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://michelesantacatterina.github.io/publication/spcd/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SCH: A structural causal framework for adaptive experiments</title>
      <link>https://michelesantacatterina.github.io/project/nih-r01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://michelesantacatterina.github.io/project/nih-r01/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Adaptive randomized clinical trials are critical in infectious disease research, offering flexibility to adjust sample sizes, introduce new interventions, discontinue ineffective treatments, and target specific subgroups to enhance treatment efficacy. This adaptability is particularly valuable in rapidly evolving public health crises, such as the development of treatments for emerging infectious diseases like COVID-19. However, adaptive trials present significant challenges, including unclear inferential targets, statistical biases from temporal and spatial variability, complexities in handling dynamic data structures, and an increased risk of false-positive findings. These concerns are reflected in recent FDA guidance on estimands, which emphasizes the need for clearly defined inferential targets, and on adaptive designs, which acknowledges that statistical bias in adaptive trials remains an understudied issue. Despite these recognized challenges, current research lacks a principled framework for structurally representing and unbiasedly estimating causal effects in adaptive trials. This project will develop a structural causal framework for adaptive trials, leveraging modern causal inference and statistical techniques alongside secondary data from the Adaptive COVID-19 Treatment Trial (ACTT)—an adaptive trial evaluating novel therapeutics in hospitalized COVID-19 patients—to enable transparent, efficient, and statistically unbiased estimation of causal effects. To achieve this, we propose the following specific aims: Aim 1: Develop a structural causal approach that deals with temporal variability. Aim 2: Extend our framework to handle spatial variability. Aim 3: Expand our framework to handle complex data structures, including failure-time and missing data, while dealing with false-positive results. Our project aligns with NIAID’s mission by advancing key methodologies for infectious disease clinical trials, particularly in adaptive designs for pandemic response, emerging pathogens, and the development of antiviral treatments. While our primary focus is on infectious disease trials, our methods have broader applicability to other disease areas, such as schizophrenia. We show this by also leveraging secondary data from schizophrenia studies, including the DECIFER trial, the RAISE study, and the EPINET study. RELEVANCE (See instructions): This research aims to improve how adaptive clinical trials are designed and analyzed. By developing methods that address key challenges in adaptive trials, our work will help ensure more accurate and reliable results, ultimately leading to better treatments and public health responses to emerging infectious diseases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;NSF Award Number&lt;/strong&gt;:   1R01AI197146-01&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Start Date&lt;/strong&gt;: August 6, 2025&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;End Date&lt;/strong&gt;:   July 31, 2029 (Estimated)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Total Intended Award Amount&lt;/strong&gt;:    $1,197,688.00&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;History of Investigator&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;br /&gt;
Michele Santacatterina (Principal Investigator, Contact)
Ivan Diaz (co-Principal Investigator)
Andrea Troxel (co-Investigator)
Donald Goff (co-Investigator)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Modern causal inference approaches to improve power for subgroup analysis in randomized controlled trials</title>
      <link>https://michelesantacatterina.github.io/publication/subgroup/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://michelesantacatterina.github.io/publication/subgroup/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Identification and estimation of causal effects using non-concurrent controls in platform trials</title>
      <link>https://michelesantacatterina.github.io/publication/nonconc/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://michelesantacatterina.github.io/publication/nonconc/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Non-parametric efficient estimation of marginal structural models with multi-valued time-varying treatments</title>
      <link>https://michelesantacatterina.github.io/publication/npmsm/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://michelesantacatterina.github.io/publication/npmsm/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Chimera: Effectively Modeling Multivariate Time Series with 2-Dimensional State Space Models</title>
      <link>https://michelesantacatterina.github.io/publication/chimera/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://michelesantacatterina.github.io/publication/chimera/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A fast bootstrap algorithm for causal inference with large data</title>
      <link>https://michelesantacatterina.github.io/publication/causalblb/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://michelesantacatterina.github.io/publication/causalblb/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;R&lt;/strong&gt; code is available here: &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/mdk31/causalbootstrap&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://github.com/mdk31/causalbootstrap&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mambamixer: Efficient selective state space models with dual token and channel selection</title>
      <link>https://michelesantacatterina.github.io/publication/mamba/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://michelesantacatterina.github.io/publication/mamba/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Stable estimation of survival causal effects</title>
      <link>https://michelesantacatterina.github.io/publication/stable_surv/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://michelesantacatterina.github.io/publication/stable_surv/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SCH: Interpretable survival analysis of complex longitudinal data</title>
      <link>https://michelesantacatterina.github.io/project/nsf-sch/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://michelesantacatterina.github.io/project/nsf-sch/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Survival analysis is a statistical technique used to predict the time until specific events occur, such as hospitalization, mechanical part failure, or customer churn. Its applications in healthcare span across public health, clinical practice, and medical research. Clinicians face the challenge of integrating complex longitudinal data from various sources, including text, images, and lab values, collected at irregular intervals, to predict patient outcomes. Traditional survival analysis methods struggle with such data. This project aims to develop novel deep learning techniques, brain-inspired computer models to analyze complex data, tailored for this purpose. Importantly, these techniques will offer interpretability specific to the healthcare domain, bolstering users&amp;rsquo; confidence in the predictions. Building upon prior work that successfully utilized X-rays and lab values to predict events like intubation, death, and ICU admission/discharge, this project will benchmark the new methods against crucial clinical applications. This interdisciplinary proposal brings together researchers specializing in computer science, biostatistics and cardiology to significantly enhance models for survival analysis in a crucial healthcare context. The research will yield new prediction methods and model interpretations, demonstrated on open datasets that explore healthcare challenges. Moreover, the proposal includes support for educational outreach programs centered around survival analysis. The investigators will collaborate with existing Cornell Tech outreach initiatives, targeting women and underrepresented minorities through partnerships with the City University of New York (CUNY) and the New York City Department of Education. By combining expertise, this project aims to drive innovation in survival analysis and promote inclusivity in STEM education.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Addressing large-scale real-world healthcare challenges with survival analysis necessitates solving complex issues related to data representation and modeling. While classical survival analysis methods like the Cox model are well-established, they do not inherently provide solutions for effective learning from long-term, irregular, and multi-modal inputs, particularly when interpretability is required. The core concept of this project revolves around a unified deep learning model for survival analysis, constructed using a Transformer backbone designed to handle complex longitudinal data. The project focuses on four key aims essential to this domain: (1) providing a unified feature representation for multi-modal data, (2) handling long-term irregularly spaced input, (3) supporting customized model interpretability through collaboration with domain experts, leveraging their expertise as soft priors, and (4) integrating this feature representation with more advanced survival analysis methodologies. The evaluation of these methods will primarily utilize the publicly available MIMIC dataset, consisting of critical care patient records. Additionally, the project team collaborates with clinicians working on heart failure, providing an additional dataset for applied evaluation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;NSF Award Number&lt;/strong&gt;:   2306556&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Start Date&lt;/strong&gt;: August 1, 2023&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;End Date&lt;/strong&gt;:   July 31, 2027 (Estimated)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Total Intended Award Amount&lt;/strong&gt;:    $1,168,412.00&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;History of Investigator&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;br /&gt;
Michele Santacatterina (Principal Investigator)
Yifan Peng (Co-Principal Investigator)
Alexander Rush (Co-Principal Investigator)
Jonathan Newman (Co-Principal Investigator)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Seminar Series, Center for Biostatistics, Mount Sinai</title>
      <link>https://michelesantacatterina.github.io/talk/msinai23/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Apr 2023 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://michelesantacatterina.github.io/talk/msinai23/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Robust weights that optimally balance confounders for estimating marginal hazard ratios</title>
      <link>https://michelesantacatterina.github.io/publication/row/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://michelesantacatterina.github.io/publication/row/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;R&lt;/strong&gt; package (with instructions on how to install the package and several examples) is available here: &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/michelesantacatterina/ROW&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://github.com/michelesantacatterina/ROW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The code for the simulations and the case studies analyses is provided here:
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/michelesantacatterina/ROW-time-to-event&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://github.com/michelesantacatterina/ROW-time-to-event&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2022 IMS International Conference on Statistics and Data Science (ICSDS)</title>
      <link>https://michelesantacatterina.github.io/talk/icsds22/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Dec 2022 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://michelesantacatterina.github.io/talk/icsds22/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Optimal Weighting for Estimating Generalized Average Treatment Effects</title>
      <link>https://michelesantacatterina.github.io/publication/gate/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://michelesantacatterina.github.io/publication/gate/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
